M Ganesh Kumar

Webpage: https://mgkumar138.github.io/ GitHub: https://mgkumar138.github.io/ GitHub: https://github.com/mgkumar138 LinkedIn: <a href="https://github.c

Summary

I am interested in understanding how the brain learns abstract concepts to solve new problems quickly and implement these principles into algorithms to improve artificial systems. My postdoctoral training is to understand the dopamine learning computations to develop model-based reinforcement learning algorithms. In my research stint at A*STAR, I developed Vision-Language models to achieve zero-shot inference on out-of-distribution datasets. During my PhD, I developed biologically plausible spatial navigation reinforcement learning models to replicate one-shot learning behavior seen in animals. Prior, I worked with human EEG and macaque neural spike data to develop Brain-Computer Interfaces.

Education

Harvard University Present

Postdoctoral training: Learning algorithms for Model-based Reinforcement Learning

- Advisors: Demba Ba (Signal processing), Cengiz Pehlevan (Theoretical Neuroscience), Lucas Janson (Statistics)
- Collaborators: Boaz Barak (Computer Science), Venkatesh Murthy (Experimental Neuroscience)
- School of Engineering and Applied Sciences (SEAS)

National University of Singapore (NUS)

January 2023

- Ph.D. Computational Neuroscience
- Doctoral thesis: Biologically plausible computations underlying one-shot learning of paired associations
- Advisors: Andrew Tan (Physiolgy), Shih-Cheng Yen (Engineering)
- Collaborators: Cheston Tan (Computer vision), Camilo Libedinsky (Psychology)
- Integrative Science and Engineering Programme (ISEP), NUS Graduate School (NGS)

National Institute of Education, Nanyang Technological University (NTU)

April 2021

Student exchange programme: Early Childhood Education & Assessment

Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT)

August 2019

- Summer school 2019: Center for Brains, Minds & Machines (CBMM)
- Project: Compositional Models for Adaptive Learning in Vision

National University of Singapore (NUS)

July 2017

- B.Sc. with Honors (Distinction) Life Sciences (Biomedical Sciences)
- Minors: University Scholars Programme (USP) and Special Programme in Science (SPS)
- Honors thesis: Wheelchair control using motor-imagery based Electroencephalogram (EEG)

Research Experience

2023 – Present	Postdoctoral Fellow, Machine Learning Foundation, Harvard University
2022 - Present	Research Scientist I, Center for Frontier Al Research (CFAR), A*STAR
2017 – 2018	Research Engineer, A*STAR Artificial Intelligence Initiative (A*AI), A*STAR
Summer 2016	Intern, Institute for Infocomm Research, A*STAR
Summer 2015	Intern, Molecular and Cellular Biology, A*STAR
Summer 2013	Intern, Environmental Health Institute, National Environmental Agency (NEA)
Fall 2013	Intern, Ministry of Education, Singapore (MOE)

Awards

- Postdoctoral Fellowship in Computer Science 2023, Harvard University
- Annual Symposium Neuroscience Singapore 2022 Best flash talk
- Al Singapore Summer school 2020 Best Poster
- MIT's Center for Brains, Minds, Machines 2019 Fujitsu Laboratories Fellow
- NUS Graduate School Scholarship (NGSS) 2018 for Ph.D.
- NUSS Gold Medal for Outstanding Achievement 2017 (Best overall student in cohort for B.Sc.)
- University Scholars Programme (USP) Senior Honor Roll 2017 (Top 10%)
- A*STAR Undergraduate Scholarship (AUS) 2013 for B.Sc.
- SINDA Excellence Awards (JC) 2013 Top 10% Singapore Indian tertiary student

Publications

- Zijun Lim*, Haidi Azaman*, <u>M Ganesh Kumar</u>, Cheston Tan. Compositional learning of word groups through embodied reinforcement learning. *Under review*.
- Leon Guertler, <u>M Ganesh Kumar</u>, Cheston Tan. Maximizing Fine-Tuning performance by augmenting LLMS to utilize Depth-Wise information. *Under review*.
- Leon Guertler, <u>M Ganesh Kumar</u>, Cheston Tan. NoiseOut: Learning to gate improves robustness in deep neural networks. *Under review*.
- M Ganesh Kumar, Elavazhagan Murugan. Trends, Innovations and Challenges in Biomedical sciences.
- Hui Min Tan, M Ganesh Kumar, Andrew Tan Yong-Yi, Shih-Cheng Yen. Spatial Representations "Right Here" and "Out There" in the Hippocampus. *Under review*.
- <u>M Ganesh Kumar</u>, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong-Yi. One-shot learning of paired association navigation using biologically plausible schemas. *Under review*.
- Clarence Lee*, <u>M Ganesh Kumar*</u>, Cheston Tan (2023). DetermiNet: A Large-Scale Diagnostic Dataset for Complex Visually-Grounded Referencing using Determiners. *Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV)*, *Paris 2023*. [GitHub]
- M Ganesh Kumar, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong-Yi (2022). A nonlinear hidden layer enables actor-critic agents to learn multiple paired association navigation. *Cerebral Cortex 32 (18)*. https://doi.org/10.1093/cercor/bhab456 [GitHub]
- M Ganesh Kumar, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong-Yi (2021). One-shot learning of paired associations by a reservoir computing model with Hebbian plasticity. arXiv preprint arXiv:2106.03580. https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.03580 [GitHub]
- M Ganesh Kumar, Kai Keng Ang, Rosa Q. So. (2017). Reject Option to reduce False Detection Rates for EEG-Motor Imagery based BCI. In Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society, EMBC 2017. 39th Annual International Conference of the IEEE. https://doi.org/10.1109/EMBC.2017.8037479

Invited talks

Apr 2023	Foundations in Machine Learning group, Harvard University
Dec 2022	Neuroscience Singapore 2022, Society for Neuroscience Singapore Chapter
Nov 2022	Senseable Intelligence group, McGovern Institute for Brain Research, MIT
Oct 2022	Metaconscious group, Brain and Cognitive Science department, MIT
Sep 2022	Department of Computational Neuroscience, Max Planck Institute for Biological Cybernetics
Jun 2022	Three-minute thesis, Department of Physiology, NUS
Feb 2022	Biolins group, Brain and Cognitive Science department, MIT
Sep 2021	Neurobiology seminar, Life Science Institute, NUS

Conference posters

M Ganesh Kumar, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong Yi. One-shot learning of paired associations using biologically plausible schemas. *RL@Harvard 2023*, *Massachusetts*, *United States*.

M Ganesh Kumar, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong Yi. One-shot learning of paired associations by a reservoir computing model with Hebbian plasticity. **Computational and Systems Neuroscience (COSYNE)** Abstracts 2022, Lisbon, Portugal.

M Ganesh Kumar, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong Yi. Learning working memory using a reservoir computing model trained by Hebbian plasticity for one-shot navigation to single displaced targets. *Neuroscience to Artificially intelligent systems (NAISys) 2022*, Virtual.

M Ganesh Kumar, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong Yi. One-shot learning of paired associations by a reservoir computing model with Hebbian plasticity. **Neuroscience 2021, Society for Neuroscience (SfN)**, Virtual.

M Ganesh Kumar, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong Yi. Learning multiple paired associations with temporal difference error modulated Hebbian plasticity. *Neuroscience to Artificially intelligent systems (NAISys) 2020*, Virtual.

<u>M Ganesh Kumar</u>, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong Yi. Learning multiple cuereward location associations using reservoir computing model & temporal difference error modulated Hebbian plasticity. *Neuromatch 2020*, Virtual.

<u>M Ganesh Kumar</u>, Cheston Tan, Camilo Libedinsky, Shih-Cheng Yen, Andrew Tan Yong Yi. Liquid State Machine acquisition of paired associations with reward modulated Hebbian learning. *Bernstein Conference 2019*, Berlin, Germany.

Ad hoc Reviewer

Journals IEEE Transactions on Cognitive and Developmental Systems

Conferences Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS),

International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)

Programming

Python - Tensorflow, PyTorch, OpenCV; Git; Matlab

Teaching

Jun 2022 STEP NUS Braincamp 2022

Oct 2021 NUS CET Beginning Artificial intelligence through Neuroscience

Jun 2021 Neuroscience, AI & Medicine workshop

Jun 2019 NUS Braincamp 2019

Jan 2019 – Dec 2019 LSM4213: Systems Neurobiology

Mentoring

May 2023 – Aug 2023 Zijun Lin, NTU Honors Project – ongoing

Mar 2023 – Aug 2023 Haidi Azaman, NUS Honors Project – pursuing M.Comp. at NUS

Sep 2022 – Mar 2023 Clarence Sheng, A*STAR Internship – on exchange at University of Bristol

Aug 2021 – Apr 2022 Xi Zhi Low, NUS Honors Project – pursuing M.D. at Duke-NUS
May 2020 – Apr 2021 Hema Prashaad, NUS Honors Project – pursuing M.D. at Duke-NUS
May 2020 – Apr 2021 Franklin Leong, NUS Honors Project – pursuing Ph.D. at ETH Zurich

Jan 2019 – Apr 2020 Graduate research mentor, Special Programme in Science

Besides research

May 2019 – Present Co-founder, Principal Consultant, ML scientist Nugen.ai

Feb 2011 – Present Operations officer (S3), Company Commander (OC) Singapore Armed Forces
Aug 2014 – Present Advisory Panel, President NUS Tamil Language Society

Jan 2019 – Dec 2019 Chairman Tamil+Al Symposium

• Entrepreneurship. I enjoy chatting with people to understand problem statements and figuring out solutions to improve outcomes. I am a Certified Scrum Product Owner (CSPO) and Scrum Master (CSM).

- Motorcycle touring. I love to ride and occasionally tour parts of South East Asia.
- Theatre productions. I have produced, directed, and acted in student theatre productions.
- Crossfit. My wife convinced me that crossfit is fun.
